<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miracles of the B. Virgin, or, An historical account of the original, and stupendious performances of the image entituled, Our Blessed Lady of Halle viz. restoring the dead to life, healing the sick, delivering of captives, &amp;c. / written originally in Latin, by Justus Lipsius ; afterwards translated into French, then into Dutch, and now rendred into English.</title>
            <title>Diva virgo Hallensis. English</title>
            <author>Lipsius, Justus, 1547-1606.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16234</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280232</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58679</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58679)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 921:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miracles of the B. Virgin, or, An historical account of the original, and stupendious performances of the image entituled, Our Blessed Lady of Halle viz. restoring the dead to life, healing the sick, delivering of captives, &amp;c. / written originally in Latin, by Justus Lipsius ; afterwards translated into French, then into Dutch, and now rendred into English.</title>
                  <title>Diva virgo Hallensis. English</title>
                  <author>Lipsius, Justus, 1547-1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint.</term>
               <term>Miracles.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58679:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Miracles of the B. Virgin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, AN Hiſtorical Account OF THE Original, and Stupendious Performances OF THE IMAGE, ENTITULED, <hi>Our Bleſſed Lady of</hi> Halle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VIZ.</hi> Reſtoring the Dead to Life, Healing the Sick, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of Captives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally in <hi>Latin,</hi> by <hi>Juſtus Lipſius;</hi> afterwards tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>French,</hi> then into <hi>Dutch,</hi> and now rendred into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Eccleſia Catholica &amp; fundata eſt Miraculis, &amp; Conſervata.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Coſterus in Ench. Cont. p. 102.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58679:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58679:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, have impoſed on the belief of Mankind ſuch Fabulous Legends, and Ridiculous Stories, that I think it a ſufficient Antidote againſt their Errors, to expoſe ſome of theſe pretended Miracles to the view of the World; it is to this that I have Tranſloted the following Relations. It will not be amiſs to give my Readers ſome account of the Book, from whence I Tranſlated theſe Relations, which I ſhall do as briefly as I can. <hi>Juſtus Lipſius</hi> publiſhed a Book in Latin, in the year <hi>1604.</hi> Intituled <hi>Diva Virgo Hallenſis Beneficia ejus, &amp; Miracula, Fide, atque Ordine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripta.</hi> This Treatiſe was Licenſed and Approved by <hi>Gulielmus de Berghes,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Camerick, Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus Floſſius</hi> Vicar General, and <hi>Gulielmus Fabritius,</hi> the Cenſor of Books. It was Tranſlated into French, and augmented by <hi>Claudius Maillard</hi> a Jeſuit; it was Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Dutch by <hi>Philip Numan,</hi> and again into French by <hi>Ludovicus du Gardin</hi> a Phyſician; it was afterwards again rendred into Dutch, with <hi>Maillards</hi> Additions, by <hi>N. N.</hi> a Jeſuit, and Printed at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> Anno <hi>1657.</hi> It is Licenſed by the Cenſor of Books, but there is a Caution in the Licenſing of it, which was not made uſe of in the Latin Edition of <hi>Lipſius;</hi> and it is, That none of theſe Miracles ſhall be received upon the Credit of the Church, unleſs, at leaſt, they be atteſted by a Biſhop, but ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:58679:3"/>taken upon the Credit of the Faithful Hiſtorian; and this was in obedience to the two Bulls of Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> to that purpoſe. It ſeems that they began to bluſh at theſe Ridiculous Stories, but yet they would have the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty believe them, though not at the expence of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith. I have in this Tranſlation moſt followed the Dutch Edition, which is divided into three parts; the firſt is ſpent in the Deſcription of the City of <hi>Halle,</hi> and the Image; which I have rather abridged than tranſlated. All that I have taken from this part, is comprized in my firſt Chapter, and is (tho an abridgment) in the Authors own words for the moſt part; the Miracles make the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, which is ſubdivided into two parts; the firſt whereof contains all the Miracles that are in <hi>Lipſius;</hi> it is this that I have taught to ſpeak Engliſh. The third part is an account of the gifts offered to the B. Virgin; <hi>Lipſius</hi>'s Treatiſe met with ſome oppoſition in the World, and was defended by <hi>Anaſtaſius Cochelet,</hi> a Camelite, and D. D. of <hi>Paris,</hi> and by <hi>Carolus Scribanius</hi> a Dutch Jeſuit.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I would not give the leaſt opportunity to the Romiſh Calumniators, to traduce me as a falſe Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, I have rendred it almoſt <hi>verbatim,</hi> though I am not Ignorant that it is eſteemed to be an Error by the best Tranſlators.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58679:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Original of the Holy Image; a ſhort Deſcription of the noble Deſcent and Vertue of the Holy <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN order to a clearer proſpect of the Original of this Holy Image,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Hall. Lipſ. c. <hi>2.</hi> ad P. Mail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard, c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> it ſeems neceſſary to enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the royal Pedigree, and conſtant Vertue of the pious <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andreas</hi> II. ſurnamed <hi>Hieroſolymitanus,</hi> the third Son of <hi>Bela</hi> III. King of <hi>Hungary;</hi> after the Death of his Brothers, inherited the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary, Anno</hi> 1201. His Queen was <hi>Gertrude,</hi> Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Mernhem, Krenten</hi> and <hi>Iſtrien,</hi> by whom he had three Sons and one Daughter, <hi>viz. Bela</hi> IV. <hi>Celomannus, Andrew</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth. Andrew</hi> being deſirous to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance himſelf, travelled to <hi>Venice,</hi> and there married a rich Wife, by whom he had a Son named <hi>Marcus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcus</hi> not being contented with the Eſtate his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left him poſſeſſed of, went to <hi>Picardy,</hi> and there married <hi>Catharine de Croy,</hi> legal Heireſs of the Houſe of <hi>Croy,</hi> deſcended from the Palſgraves of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Wittenberg;</hi> from this Marriage ſprung that illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Family of <hi>Croy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (which moſt ſerves our Deſign) Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as above, of <hi>Andrew</hi> II. King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Aunt to <hi>Marcus;</hi> at the Age of three Years, was by Ambaſſadors betrothed to <hi>Lewis</hi> Son of <hi>Hermon,</hi> Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave of <hi>Thuringia</hi> and <hi>Haſſia,</hi> deſcended from <hi>Charles</hi> the Great. At the Age of four Years ſhe was conveyed to <hi>Thuringia,</hi> to be educated in her Bridegrooms Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58679:4"/>Court. It would be tedious to relate the Signs of a Pious Diſpoſition, viſible in her Infancy.</p>
               <p>It ſhall ſuffice to remark, That being then a Virgin, and afterwards both Wife and Widow, her vertuous Deportment in all theſe Eſtates rendered her Famous: The Painters and Carvers repreſented her with three Crowns on her Head; intimating that ſhe had merited a Crown from each State. At the Age of fourteen, ſhe was married to <hi>Lewis,</hi> and had Iſſue by him, <hi>viz. Hermannus</hi> (who did not live long) and <hi>Sophia,</hi> alſo another Daughter of the ſame Name, or according to ſome, her Name was <hi>Gertrude;</hi> ſhe left this World for a Cloyſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> accompanying the Emperor <hi>Frederick,</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the conqueſt of the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> dyed in <hi>Apulia,</hi> or as ſome affirm in <hi>Sicilie.</hi> His Body was ſent to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who with extraordinary Grief interr'd it. <hi>Henry</hi> her Husbands Brother, after many Injuries of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to her, not only bereft her of all her Eſtate, but baniſhed her ſo haſtily, that ſhe could hardly find a Place of Ropoſe for herſelf and Children. She retired to <hi>Marpurg</hi> in <hi>Haſſia;</hi> where after having ſpent four Years in all manner of vertuous Exerciſes, by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of one <hi>Conrad,</hi> a religious Man, ſhe departed this Life, being but twenty four Years of Age, <hi>Anno</hi> 1231. Her Sanctity and Miracles cauſed Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> IX. to add her to the number of the Saints, <hi>Anno</hi> 1235.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophia</hi> her eldeſt Daughter, and Heireſs rather of her Vertue than Eſtate, went into the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> where ſhe was married to <hi>Henry</hi> II. Duke of <hi>Brabant.</hi> He had <hi>Henry</hi> III. by his firſt Dutcheſs <hi>Maria van Swa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> Daughter to the Emperor <hi>Philip.</hi> He had alſo by <hi>Sophia</hi> another <hi>Henry,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>The Brabander:</hi> He with the Aſſiſtance of his Mother, made divers At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58679:4"/>for the acquiſition of their Inheritance, which the ſtrength of the adverſe Party rendered ineffectual: But at laſt he regained <hi>Haſſia,</hi> and leſt his Poſterity poſſeſt of it, more by the Prayers of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> than the Aſſiſtance of his Mother. But leaving this neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hiſtory, let us come to thoſe things for which cauſe it was related.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophia,</hi> Inheritrix of her Mothers Piety, being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to follow her Example in all things, was ſtrongly inclined to the Veneration and Love of our B. Lady. 'Tis really believed, That her Mother bequeathed her ſome Images of the B. Virgin, which in remembrance of her, ſhe loved and eſteemed more than ordinary; whereof ſhe gave one to the Cloyſter of <hi>Carmelite Nuns</hi> at <hi>Vilvord,</hi> which hath been antiently as famous for its Miracles as of late; its title is, <hi>Our B. Lady of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation;</hi> intimating that ſeveral Perſons have there been delivered from their Maladies, and acquired eaſe both of Body and Mind. She gave three other Images to <hi>Mechtildis,</hi> Siſter to Duke <hi>Henry,</hi> her Husband, who being a Widow had married <hi>Florentius</hi> IV. Earl of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> from which Nuptials ſprung the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>William</hi> II. who was in the contention choſen Emperour of <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mechtildis</hi>'s reception of theſe Images of <hi>Sophia,</hi> in proceſs of Time had a better Effect than could have been, if ſhe had received them from <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her ſelf, who had been long dead; and the great Diſtance that was between their ſeveral Habitations, might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented any Acquaintance between them. <hi>Mechtildis</hi> not long before her Deceaſe, diſtributed the Images in divers Places: She placed one at <hi>Graveſand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lipſ. hiſ. Hall. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> an antient though ſmall City of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſituate near the Cloyſter of <hi>Loosduynen,</hi> which ſhe had founded, and where after
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58679:5"/>her Husbands Death, ſhe piouſly and chaſtly ſpent the remainder of her Life. She gave another to the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melites</hi> Church at <hi>Haerlem.</hi> And the third (which is our Image) ſhe beſtowed at <hi>Halle</hi> in <hi>Henegow:</hi> But why was this placed there? I believe becauſe her Daughter <hi>Adelheydis</hi> was married to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Avennes,</hi> Earl of <hi>Henogowe,</hi> ſome Years before her Death. To which we may add,<note place="margin">Die A. <hi>1267.</hi> geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiedenis. Lipſ. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> That ſhe had a Daughter of her own Name, who being married to the Earl of <hi>Hennen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> had at one Birth 364 Children, which were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized altogether by the Biſhop of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht:</hi> An Event that looks more like a Fable than a true Hiſtory, did not our Annals ſo firmly and unanimouſly aſſert it. But to return to our Deſign, as the ſtubborn were apt to calumniate, ſo the Religious admired by what means the Holy <hi>Elizabeth</hi> collected ſo many Images of the <hi>B. Virgin.</hi> Both which may be ſatisfied by <hi>Harae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who ſays,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>1</hi> Ann. l. <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> That ſhe her ſelf, or ſome Body for her, received them from her Aunt, the religious <hi>Heduwigis,</hi> (Wife to <hi>Hedricus Barbatus</hi> Prince of <hi>Sleſia</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) who knew the vertuous Diſpoſition of her Neece. The Reaſon of this Conjecture might be, That in her life time, ſhe was found to have a great quantity of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the B. Virgin, which ſhe very much reverenced: She kept a ſmall one commonly in her Hand, as well to excite her Devotion with the ſight of it, as to bleſs and heal the Sick: Nay, which is more, ſhe ſo venerated that Sacred Image, that ſhe dyed with one between her Fingers, and was in that Poſture interr'd. Some Years after her death, her Body was found conſumed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the two Fingers, which with their former Vigor graſpt the ſacred Image. This is the Reaſon why the Painters repreſent her with an Image in her Hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58679:5"/>To ſpeak more particularly, This holy Image is compoſed of Wood, it is about three Foot high, ſitting on a Chair and offering her left Breaſt to the Child to ſuck, the Cloaths and other Ornaments veil it from our Eyes: It is not eſteemed for its compoſure, nor the Matter whereof it is compoſed, (that being ſlight and common) nor its black Colour, cauſed by its Antiquity, and the Smoak of Lamps; but there is a more than Human Majeſty attends it, becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the B. Virgin, who is ſo honourable, and hath done ſo many Miracles, and doth daily. That Character, <hi>Nigra ſum, ſed formoſa,</hi> might here take Place! This Meanneſs of the Image, ought not to diminiſh Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Devotion, nor the Veneration of the Simple and Illiterate. Here that falls in very opportunely which <hi>Wichmans</hi> remarks, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brab. Mar. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> That amongſt all the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Images of the B. Virgin (eſpecially thoſe that were found in the <hi>Netherlands</hi>) there was none whoſe matter was ſumptuous, or compoſure elegant. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would not be eſteemed, were not their worth enhanced by Faith; which neglecting the Curioſities of the Image, fixes it ſelf upon the mighty Power of God, which appears through the Images in the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miracles. This gives us a clear Proſpect of the Divine Providence, in bereaving the World of all Occaſions of Idolatry by this meanneſs of the Images; for on the contrary, had they been elegant and coſtly, the unthinking Vulgar would have appropriated their Honour and Veneration to their Splendor; and the Obſtinate would think and affirm, That we therefore honour the Type, but not for the Sake of the Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type: Yet we ought not to hinder the making of coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Images in honour of the B. Virgin, for they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her as well, nay better than the meaner, if they be miraculous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58679:6"/>The B. Virgin began to be honoured in this Image, and to perform various Miracles about the Year 1267. in the time of <hi>Nicholas de la Fountaine</hi> the fifty firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Camerick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beverlink theat. <hi>L.</hi> E. V. Epus.</note> a Man of extraordinary Piety and Vertue; and as his Suffragan <hi>Thomas Cantipratanus</hi> (who was born at <hi>Leew</hi> near <hi>Halle</hi>) affirms, a great Honourer of the B. Virgin, a worthy Scholar to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Magnus,</hi> and School-fellow with <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> all ardent Lovers of the Mother of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Bleſſed Virgin defended the City of <hi>Halle</hi> from the Power of her Enemies.</head>
               <p>LEt us now with a thankful Acknowledgment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the wonderful and memorable Actions, which the Queen of Heaven, and Mother of Mercy hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to ſo many afflicted and comfortleſs Perſons. And here we muſt not omit, That the wooden Image, which is ſeveral hundred Years old, and yet is ſo far from the uſual Concomitants of Antiquity, that it is not in the leaſt injured by Time, nor the frequent Fires, which the Neighbours affirm have conſumed the adjacent Houſes.</p>
               <p>The B. Virgin hath not only preſerv'd her Image and Church from the impetuous Flames; but hath ſeveral Times defended the City againſt the Power and Force of its Enemies</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip Cleve,</hi> in the Year 1489. (chief of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Maximilian</hi> I. and his Son <hi>Philip</hi>) ſeeing that <hi>Halle</hi> was a Thorn in the Foot of the <hi>Bruſſellers,</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly bought ſome of the Burghers to his ſide, that when he ſhould come, they ſhould give him entrance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58679:6"/>into the City; he was on his March with 6000. Men, and had ſurprized the City, had not a Burgher of <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> by chance (why ſay I by chance, it was by the appointment of the B. Virgin, who watched over her City) been impriſoned, who diſcovered the Plot: The Burghers made uſe of this Diſcovery, and let <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Cleve</hi> march on with his Army, paſs the Moat, and climb the Walls, and then with an extraordinary Courage forced him to retire with Shame and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> ſeeing the ill Succeſs of his firſt Aſſault, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing procured more Strength, and armed himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, made a ſecond Aſſault; he had now 10000. Men, his Deſign was carried on with ſuch Speed, that he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized twenty Souldiers in the Fields without the City; the City was guarded with no ſtronger a Garriſon than 250. Men, which rendred his Diſhonour the greater. He planted his Ordnance, and battered down ſo much of the Walls, that three Wagons could go in abreaſt; others ſhot with Bombs ſo violently, that many Houſes were in Danger of burning. In this apparent Danger, the Burghers were thunder-ſtrook with Fear and Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: All human Helps were ineffectual, which cauſed them to rely on the Goodneſs of <hi>Heaven.</hi> They applyed themſelves unto the Bleſſed Virgin, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing encouraged by an Expectation of her Help, and accompanied with ſpiritual Aſſiſtances, they reſiſted ſo ſtoutly, that by Sun-ſet, the Enemy having loſt his Men and Courage, was forced to raiſe the Siege, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaiming, That it was more than human Power that vanquiſhed him. During the Fight the Women were very buſie in quenching the injected Fire; there was ten Women in one Houſe, ſo much endangered, that all people thought they had been choaked or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58679:7"/>burned; but they were delivered without any great Damage, and went each of them to her own Houſe.</p>
               <p>There was none in <hi>Halle,</hi> whoſe countenance did not expreſs an extraordinary Joy, and there was a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and univerſal Thankſgiving to the B. Virgin. On the next Day the Enemy being reſolved to hazard ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aſſault, there arrived a Meſſenger from the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Croy</hi> to the Burghers, promiſing them his Aſſiſtance within three Days: This cauſed an extraordinary Joy to poſſeſs the Citizens Minds, which ſhewed it ſelf in beating of Drums and ringing of Bells: This unuſual Triumph raiſed a Suſpicion and Fear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Enemies, which hurried them to ſo haſty a Flight, as forced them to leave their Dead and Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Appurtenances behind them in the City-Moats, and in the Way. In Remembrance of this great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, there was reſerved one hundred Iron and Stone Bowls, weighing ſome thirty, others forty, and ſome ſixty Pound: By this we may ſee the Strength of thoſe Cities (though weakly fenced) which the B. Virgin hath choſen to govern.</p>
               <p>For the Remembrance of this Victory, the Burghers ſpend the Even of the tenth of <hi>July</hi> in all Expreſſions of Joy, and the Morning in Devotion; they ſing a ſolemn Thankſgiving-Maſs, and carry the Hoſt in Proceſſion along the Streets and Walls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Puniſhment of two Blaſpheemers.</head>
               <p>WE will deſcend a little to our Times, and by an Action worthy of Deriſion, evince the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Praiſe of the B. Virgin.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58679:7"/>In the Time of the bloody <hi>Netherland</hi>-Wars,<note place="margin">1580.</note> 
                  <hi>Oliver vanden Tempel</hi> had the chief Charge of the Magazeen in <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> The City of <hi>Halle,</hi> as alſo <hi>Henegow</hi> and <hi>Artois,</hi> put themſelves under the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: This ſo enraged <hi>Oliver,</hi> that he marched twice couragiouſly againſt the City, thinking that none of the neighbouring Cities (which were all his Allies) would hinder his Deſign: There was ſcarſe forty Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the City, the Citizens young and inexpert; for all this he was couragiouſly beaten off the firſt Day: Then under Pretence of a feigned Retreat, he ſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently for all the Souldiers out of the neighbouring Cities, and came again before <hi>Halle</hi> with more Strength, before they knew of it. His Souldiers being on their March, heightened the Valour of each other with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Speeches; amongſt the reſt, one <hi>John Swickius</hi> an impious Fellow, ſaid, He would cut off the Noſe of our little Lady of <hi>Halle</hi> (ſo he called the B. Virgin). They came before the City, and when both Sides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Shoot, a Musket-bullet took off <hi>Swickius</hi>'s Noſe, (it was undoubtedly directed by the B. Virgin.)</p>
               <p>But <hi>John Riſſelmans</hi> was more inſolent and rude: This Villain ſaid, That he would carry the Image of the B. Virgin to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and make a Bonefire with it. This Impious Calumniator thought not of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Fire that ſhortly after reached him; For a Cannon-Bullet hit him, and carried his Jaw along with it, which was the Cauſe of his Death ſhortly after. This was the Fortune of thoſe that came to fight againſt the City of <hi>Halle,</hi> that is againſt the B. Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58679:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A Servant having loſt his Maſters Falcon, and being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ladder to die for it, was delivered from his approaching Death, by the Aſſiſtance of the B. Virgin.</head>
               <p>THe following Relation is atteſted by antient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and an old Wooden Image, although Time hath bereft us of the Year when it was done, and the Names of the Perſons. The Dutch Nobility (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were deſtroyed by War) were great Lovers of Hawking and Fowling; for this End they had divers expert and coſtly Hawks brought unto them from the North. A Nobleman, whoſe Severity is better known to us than his Name, was addicted to this Exerciſe, and had a Falcon which he highly eſteemed; this Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, either by an unhappy Chance, or the careleſneſs of the Falconer, flew away paſt recovery: The Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man underſtanding his Loſs, was ſo enraged that he ſwore, If his Servant did not find his Falcon within five Weeks, his Head ſhould ſatisfie the Loſs. He made all poſſible ſearch in Woods and all other likely Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but in Vain, the Falcon was irrecoverably loſt: At the five Weeks end, he could not prevail with his Lord for one Weeks Reſpite, but he ſtill perſiſting in his Reſolution, cauſed a Gallows to be immediately erected before his Houſe, the Executioner bound his Eyes and led him up the Ladder, ſtanding with the Rope about his Neck, he remembred <hi>Halle,</hi> And your Mercy, O Bleſſed Virgin! which he ſhortly after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, yea it even met his Devotions; for while he was at his Prayers, and directed his Heart to You, he thought that he heard the clapping of the Wings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58679:8"/>of a Fowl, which gave him ſome Hope, he deſired his Maſter that his Eyes might be unbound, that he might ſend his Prayers to Heaven with a Freedom of Sight; his Requeſt was granted, then renewing his Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Bleſſed Virgin, the Falcon flew ſwiftly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the almoſt dying Perſon, and ſettled upon his Shoulder. Some affirm, That the Falcon came not until he had been turned off the Ladder; but this is not atteſted by the Image which he offered. All the Spectators congratulated his Preſervation, and wiſhed him all Felicity, and he rendred Praiſe and Honour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the B. Virgin. His Lord might with his Falcon catch Partridges, but on that Day the B. Virgin caught the beſt Prey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> One was delivered from Drowning.</head>
               <p>THat the Mercy of the Mother of God is more abundant than the Waters, <hi>Paſlinus</hi> ſhall evince,<note place="margin">1380. 1 <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> who was a Burgher of <hi>Enghen</hi> in <hi>Henegow.</hi> In <hi>Auguſt</hi> in this little City, aroſe ſuch a grievous Tempeſt, mixt with hard Thunderbolts, dreadful Lightning, and thick black Rain, that the ſwelling Springs, Stone-ways, Houſes and Water-mills, were waſhed away by the prevailing Stream, and turned the Land into a Sea; all now ſought ſome Refuge, one got up on high to preſerve himſelf from Water, another crept into a Hole for Shelter againſt the Lightning. <hi>Paſlinus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf to his Cellar, as well to preſerve himſelf, as ſome Victuals, and Houſhold-ſtuff; as he was buſie there, he was over-run with Water, there was no Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Flighht, nor Hopes of human Help: He
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58679:9"/>reſolved in this extream Neceſſity with a Prayer to commit himſelf to the Charge of the B. Virgin; and immediately he found help, for he eſpied a little above a Door, which he caught hold of, and hung there two Hours, yet the Water was up to his Chin, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it riſe above his Head, but did not continue ſo any Time; the approaching Night filled him with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Apprehenſions of its length, and made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new his Supplications to the B. Virgin, who caſt forth her bright Beams, and conſiderablely increaſed his Strength, inabling him to keep his Hold at the Door until the next Day, and his Deliverance appeared, for on the Morning the Waters were ſunk; yet he underſtood, to his great Grief, that his Wife and Child were drowned in the Inundation. He offered a Waxen-Image in Honour of the B. Virgin, and came accompanied with ſeventeen Witneſſes to return her Thanks; for it was ſhe alone that kept him from his approaching Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A drowned Child reſtored to Life.</head>
               <p>A Houſe accompanied with many Children and much Water, fills the Parents Hearts with Fears. A young Child unhappily evinced the Truth of this, to his Fathers Grief, and the Glory of the B. Virgin. The Father miſſing his Son, after having ſpent two Hours in a vain Search for him feared that Misfortune which afterwards happened; for he found him drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Pool, his Head in the Mud, and his Feet out of the Water; he drew him out, but found no Sign of Life remaining in him: After he had lain thus a full
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58679:9"/>Hour the Father caſt a ſorrowful Eye towards his Child, and ſent a Prayer for Mercy to You, O Bleſſed Mother! His Thoughts had hardly reached <hi>Halle,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Child was reſtored to Life and began to ſtir, and to riſe up, and walked home with his Father. The Waters of Death abound in all Places, but in <hi>Halle</hi> there flows a Fountain of Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> A Perſon poſſeſſed by the Devil, was diſpoſſeſſed.</head>
               <p>IF an ill Gueſt be a great Burthen, how bad muſt it then be for a Man to harbour his worſt Enemy, not only in his Houſe but in his Body. <hi>Reynier Willegem</hi> a Burgher of <hi>Oudenaerde,</hi> a ſtout Man and of a robuſt Body, was after our Ladies Aſcenſion-day poſſeſt by the Devil; this helliſh Spirit ſeized him as followeth, He raved and foamed, and tore himſelf and others, his Countenance ſufficiently evidenced the Malignity of his Gueſt. His Friends knew no better Remedy than to invoke the Aid of our Lady of <hi>Halle;</hi> their Prayers were heard, the Devil ejected, and <hi>Reynier</hi> regained his priſtine Liberty. That helliſh Serpent might well fear, That our B. Lady would not ſpare his Members, whoſe Head ſhe had broken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> A Child being Blind and Diſeaſed was cured.<note place="margin">This in the Original is in Verſo.</note>
               </head>
               <p>THis Childs Name was <hi>Nicholas,</hi> his Father lived at <hi>Liege:</hi> This <hi>Nicholas</hi> was not only Blind but very Weak and Infirm; The Fame of the Bleſſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58679:10"/>Virgin of <hi>Halle</hi> having reached that place, the Father addreſſed himſelf to her in behalf of his Son; who had both his Sight and Health reſtored unto him, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a Silver-Image in Honour of the B. Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Some delivered from Shipwrack.</head>
               <p>WE have hitherto confined our Diſcourſe to the Land, let us now plunge our ſelves into the midſt of a horrible Tempeſt, and there behold the Star of the Sea, the B. Virgin ſhooting the Beams of her Mercy.<note place="margin">1405.</note> A Ship which departed from <hi>Holland</hi> being bound for <hi>Antwerp,</hi> encountred a dreadful Storm on its Way thither, and the approaching Night doubled the Danger, and the Fears of thoſe on Board her, and the Pilot told them the Ship was loſt, alſo that he had done all that he could, and adviſed every one to think upon his Soul, that they might reach the Heaven of Felicity. This made them fill the Air with Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Cries, and Prayers: One of the Seamen ſaid unto them, Wherefore do we not betake our ſelves to the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle?</hi> They immediately followed his Counſel, and preſently a bright Light viſible above the Ship diſpelled the Clouds of Night from their Eyes, and thoſe of Fear from their Hearts, and conducted the Ship to its deſired Key. The Maſter with ſome of the Men (like another <hi>Noah</hi>) went to <hi>Halle,</hi> to preſent his Thank-offering to the B. Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58679:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> A Gentlewoman was delivered from her Diſtraction.</head>
               <p>HE that hath the Uſe of his Senſes enjoys many Bleſſings that are not taken notice of, but the want of them renders a Man poor.<note place="margin">1407.</note> This was exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in a young Gentlewoman of the Houſe of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerelle,</hi> who being very Beautiful, and of a healthful Conſtitution, became Diſtracted; her Mother ſpared neither Labour nor Charge for her Curing, although it proved Ineffectual; ſhe then had Recourſe to <hi>Halle,</hi> and by an ardent Prayer, recommended the miſerable Eſtate of her Daughter to our Lady, and whilſt ſhe was at her Devotions in the Church, the Mother of Mercy performed a Miracle at Home, for her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was cured at the very ſame Time.</p>
               <p>She came to thank the B. Virgin, and offered a Waxen-image of 110 <hi>l.</hi> weight correſpondent to the Weight of her Daughter; but the Miracle can never be overweighed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> A Boy was delivered from Drowning in the <hi>Maze.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Hocy</hi> five Boys went into a Boat,<note place="margin">1408.</note> they lanched into the River and wantonly played together in the Boat; but their Sport had not continued long, ere the ſwelling of the <hi>Maze</hi> and Strength of the Winds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted it, and toſſed the Boat ſo violently, that they could hardly get to the Shore: But as ſoon as they were got to Land, four of them leapt out of the Boat,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58679:11"/>and with their leaping made the Boat fly back on the Water, the fifth, who was about fourteen Years Old, remained in the Boat; immediately the Wind and Waves toſſed the Boat aloft, and preſently plunged it into the Deep, and turned it upſide down ſo violently that the unfortunate Boy was thrown out amongſt the Waves; the four that had leaped Aſhore, by their Cries drew the People to the Water-ſide, and amongſt the reſt the Boys Mother: What could ſhe do? ſhe ſaid, O B. Virgin who art honoured at <hi>Halle,</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that I will come thither with my Son to ſerve you, if it will pleaſe you to deliver him from his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Death. The Vow was hardly uttered, ere he was driven towards the Bridg by the mighty Force of the Waters, he paſſed the Arches of the Bridg unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, and floated along amongſt the Waves about the ſpace of half a Mile, to a place where the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing River ſoftly laid him down.</p>
               <p>O wonderful Goodneſs! the Boy wreſtled with the Waves, and was as it were carried in the ſoft Arms of the bleſſed Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> A Child which was Strangled was reſtored to Life.</head>
               <p>IN the City of <hi>Bins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1419.</note> there was a poor Chair-Woman, by name <hi>Catharine;</hi> ſhe had a ſmall Child whoſe Name was <hi>Chriſtopher;</hi> being gone abroad to work on <hi>Eaſter-eve,</hi> one of her Neighbours knocked at her Door, and finding it ſlightly ſhut entred the Houſe, poor People who have nothing to loſe have no Cauſe of Fear: This Woman found the Child hanging out of the Cradle and ſtrangled; it is probable that the Child
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58679:11"/>in the abſence of his Mother, turning it ſelf to and fro, rolled out of the Cradle, and remained hung in the Swathing-band. The Woman ſeeing this, fell to cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and calling, which brought ſeveral people thither; as alſo the Mother of the Infant, who being aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and frighted at the accident ſwooned away, but the by-ſtanders brought her to her ſelf again, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd her, and adviſed her, to offer up her Child to our Lady of <hi>Halle,</hi> which ſhe did with a good courage, and diſtinct words: And behold the Child which was ſtiff, and had been above three hours dead, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately revived, and eat and drank that which was given to it. The Mother afterwards offered it up to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin of <hi>Halle,</hi> according to her promiſe; being accompanied with the noble Lady of <hi>Scarſinne,</hi> and other creditable Perſons at <hi>Halle.</hi> And ſhould not the B. Virgin cauſe ſuch a grieved Mother, and her Infant, to rejoyce, who as on the day following had received an unſpeakable Conſolation, by the Reſurrection of her Son.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> A Girl that was drowned in a Well, was reſtored to life.</head>
               <p>IT is a Proverb, <hi>The deeper the Well,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1419.</note> 
                  <hi>the clearer the Water;</hi> to which I add the more excellent Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. This was obvious in the Caſtle of <hi>Ligny,</hi> and evinced in the Perſon of <hi>Johanna Mallart,</hi> who went to draw Water for the uſe of the Family, out of a Well about 40 foot deep, and the top was laid round with Bricks, having before it a great Stone, againſt which people leaned. As the Girl was drawing up a Bucket, this ſtone, and ſhe with it, fell into the Well, and was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58679:12"/>drowned; in this fall there was another Evil, for in the Well there jetted out a piece of a Rock, upon which ſhe fell with ſuch a force, that not only wounded her Head, and her Arm, but which was worſt, ſhe ſo hurt her Leg, that it was ſwelled as big as her Body: She remained half an hour in the Water before ſhe was drawn out; ſhe was dead, her countenance being very black and filthy. She was in this condition 3 hours; her Mother was a ſorrowful Spectotor all the time: But a Ray of Conſolation diſplayed it ſelf, for as ſoon as ſhe (by the advice of the by-ſtanders) had offer'd up her Prayers, and her Daughter, to our Lady of <hi>Halle, Joanna</hi> reviv'd, regain'd her former Colour, and her Wounds were healed. Her Mother and ſhe came to <hi>Halle</hi> to return thanks to the B. Virgin.</p>
               <p>Here alſo I ſhould add a Relation of a little Boy, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> years before was drowned in a Well at <hi>Obbruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> and through the compaſſion of the Mother of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy revived. May not the B. Virgin then ſay in the words of the Wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. <hi>He that findeth me findeth life, and Wells of Salvation from the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> A Child after it had been three days Dead and Buried, was reſtored to life.<note place="margin">the Original.</note>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Seneffe,</hi> a Village of <hi>Brabant,</hi> not far from <hi>Halle,</hi> (as is aſſerted by unqueſtionable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) there was a Child ſtill-born; it continued in that ſtate three days, and was alſo buried. The ſorrowful Mother had ſpent a whole day in Tears, and in the evening ſhe thought ſhe ſaw a Woman of an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Miene, and cheerful Countenance; who told
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58679:12"/>her, If ſhe would make a vow to our Lady of <hi>Halle,</hi> her Child ſhould live: The Mother promis'd that ſhe would go to <hi>Halle</hi> to ſerve the Bleſſed Virgin, and being comforted by this Woman, would have the Child taken out of the Grave, which was done, and the Child laid Dead, and ſtiff in its Mothers Lap: Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the pale Colour began to vaniſh from its Cheeks, and the Child revived, and was baptized; and at Noon it dy'd again, and its Soul went to the Coeleſtial Court; to render Honour and Praiſe to the Bleſſed Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Two Dead Children reſtored to Life.</head>
               <p>ANother Child at <hi>Cantimpre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1427. March 7.</note> unhappily loſt and killed its ſelf; his Fathers Name was <hi>John Bidans,</hi> who with its Mother, the Family and Neighbours ſpent two days and a night, in a vain ſearch after the Child; the Father very zealouſly vowed to go on Pilgrimage to our Bleſſed Lady of <hi>Halle,</hi> and renewing their ſearch, they found him ſmothered in a Muddy Pool; and truſting upon the mercy of the Bleſſed Virgin, they laid him upon her Altar; the Corps feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power of that adjacent Mother, which bore unto us eternal life, revived, ſpoke and walked, in the preſence of <hi>Nicholas</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cantimpre,</hi> and a great multitude of people. The Father coming to <hi>Halle,</hi> might joyfully ſay, My Son was loſt and is found, was Dead, and is riſen again.</p>
               <p>But that which I am about to add, is more ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious. At St. <hi>Hilaries,</hi> a ſmall Village near <hi>Camerick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1428.</note> lived one <hi>Stephen Morel,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Fermine,</hi> who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58679:13"/>was delivered of a Dead Child, which the Midwife, and all the reſt of the Women preſent at her delivery atteſted: They had now no more to do but to Bury the unbaptized Child in unhallowed Earth; which they performed. In this condition it remained fifteen days, and was forgotten by all but the Mother, in whoſe thoughts it was deeply impreſſed. It troubled her moſt that her Child was not only bereft of this ſhort, but an Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>This raiſed ſuch a commotion in the mind of the Religious Mother, (Religious I ſay, becauſe ſhe came every year to ſerve our Bleſſed Lady of <hi>Halle</hi>) that ſhe made a Vow, and daily renewed it, her Faith encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the ordinary courſe of Nature. Things conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in this poſture until the fifteenth day from her unhappy Delivery, when ſhe was aſſur'd by a Viſion, that her Child was alive; ſhe forced her Husband and ſome Women to go to the Grave, to examine the truth of it: They digg'd up the Earth 3 foot deep, for ſo deep the Child lay, and behold! (Oh ſtupendious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle!) they found the ſame Child living, and as freſh as a Blooming Roſe.</p>
               <p>They acquainted the Pariſh Prieſt with this Miracle, who found their Report to be true, for he ſaw in the Child clear evidences of life; but becauſe the Child was Dedicated to our Lady, he adviſed them to carry it to <hi>Vertigneuil,</hi> a neighbouring Village, where our Lady was very much honoured. The Midwife and the Women, with other people, went thence on the Evening; the Village was ſcituate two miles diſtant; the Prudent Mother gave them a piece of a hallowed Candle, to put into a Lanthorn to light themſelves along. And behold another Wonder! That ſmall piece of Candle, not two Inches long, burned from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58679:13"/>ſix of the Clock in the Evening, until the next day, without the leaſt diminution. In their Journey, a third Wonder appear'd, before them it was light as the Day, but behind them a very dark Night. They ſet out ſo late, and walked ſo ſlowly, for fear of injuring the Child, that it was late in the Night e're they arrived at <hi>Vertigneuil.</hi> 'Tis to be ſuppoſed that they lodged there, burning in the interim the hallowed Candle by the Child. The next morning, as ſoon as it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day light, they went to the Prieſts Lodging, but not finding him there, they heard that he was gone to the Caſtle of <hi>Vertain,</hi> upon ſome affair. The Father and the Church-Wardens Wife went preſently thither, when they came there it was Noon, and they found all the Gates ſhut; they knock'd, but in vain, for no body opened them. Behold now a fourth Wonder! The Portal of the firſt Gate opened its ſelf, alſo the Portals of the ſecond and third Gate, opened of their own accord; and they came into the Chamber where the Governour, the Prieſt, and others were, without the knowledge of any in the Caſtle. <hi>Henry Damman,</hi> who was Governour of the Caſtle, began to demand whether they were Friends or Enemies, and run at the Porter with his Sword, to Revenge the Treachery he thought him guilty of; but having with aſtoniſhment heard the reaſon of their coming, and the opening of the Portals, he and the gueſts, about twenty in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, would accompany the Prieſt to the Baptizing of ſuch a Child. When they came where the Infant was, they ſaw in it remarkable Tokens of life, it bled at the Noſe, opened its Mouth and Eyes, it ſighed, and wept great tears. This firmly aſſured the Prieſt, and all the Spectators, that it was alive; the Prieſt Baptized it in the Preſence of almoſt Seventy Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58679:14"/>And preſently after (is not this the fifth Miracle) they ſaw it evidently waſt and decay like Snow; it died there, and was Buried in Sanctify'd Earth. The ſame hour the Mother <hi>Firmine</hi> felt her Breaſt to dry, which before was full of Milk. This Miracle was ſeen, and atteſted by two whole Villages: Oh wonderful thing! What can Impudence? Yea Calumny its ſelf, ſay againſt theſe Miracles? Bleſſed be thou, O Bleſſed Virgin, which bore in thy Womb everlaſting life, and through thy Mercy and Interceſſion gave life, both of Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the Dead, and made him partaker of eternal life. Keep in us the life of Grace, that we may enjoy a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Death, a joyful Reſurrection, and everlaſting Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and live in it with thee, and thy Son for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> An innocent Man wonderfully delivered from the Gallows.</head>
               <p>IF the Mother of God be ready to help the impious, how can ſhe then neglect the innocent ſeeking her aid, it is far from her mercy and goodneſs ſo to do. This was exemplified in the perſon of <hi>John Sampenoy;</hi> who,<note place="margin">1405.</note> coming from <hi>Aſpernay</hi> in <hi>Champagine,</hi> to <hi>Halle,</hi> to offer his Devotions to the Bleſſed Virgin, on the way he got two Treacherons companions, <hi>Nicholat Barren,</hi> and <hi>Peter Le Norman,</hi> who underſtanding the cauſe of his Journey, told him that they alſo were going to <hi>Halle,</hi> but not for the ſake of Devotion, but profit, for they were Merchants.</p>
               <p>Theſe two were purſued, and taken at <hi>Avennes</hi> for Thieves, and Legally convicted of Robbery: They were put upon the Rack, whereupon they confeſſed that they had ſtole, and Sold four Silver Cups, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58679:14"/>withal accuſed <hi>Sampenoy</hi> of being Guilty with them of the Theft; and receiving a third part thereof; alſo they ſaid that they had Murthered a Man on the way, and <hi>Sampenoy</hi> had aſſiſted them, hereupon they were led to Execution, but <hi>Nicholas</hi> upon the Gallows cleared <hi>Sampenoy,</hi> and recalled his falſe accuſation; but <hi>Peter Le Norman</hi> perſiſted in his acccuſation, affirming that <hi>John</hi> was alike guilty with him, and that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this with his Death. The Judge proceeded, and hanged <hi>Sampenoy</hi> with the other two, notwithſtanding his conſtant aſſertion of his Innocence; the Judge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the people to hear a Maſs for his Soul, to which <hi>Sampenoy</hi> replied, <q>No my Lord, I had rather they would recite a <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> and an <hi>Ave Mary,</hi> in honour of the Bleſſed Virgin of <hi>Halle,</hi> to whom I was going, and becauſe my innocence cannot help me here, I appeal to her, and deſire that ſhe would pleaſe to defend me.</q> He was then turned off the Ladder, but ſtill continued alive, the Executioner in a paſſion leapt upon his ſhoulders, that he might ſtrangle him with his weight: but for all this he remained alive, ſeeing clearly, (as he after related) a Beautiful Woman, of a Majeſtick aſpect, who embraced him, and took him into her protection. More than an hour had been ſpent on this manner, to the amazement of all the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, when <hi>John de Selles,</hi> a Gentleman, came riding with full ſpeed to thither, and ſaid to the Judge, <q>My Lord, I deſire that you would pleaſe to give me this innocent man, or rather give him to our Lady, in whoſe name and was by whoſe command I came hither.</q> 
                  <hi>Sampenoy</hi> was immediately cut down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, and began to thank the Gentleman; but he told him, that it was the Mother of God which had wrought his deliverance, whom he was obliged to go
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58679:15"/>
                  <hi>Halle</hi> to ſerve. It is Proverb, That a man had better be given over by ten Phyſitians, than be condemned by one Judge; but they that hide themſelves under the wings of the B. Virgin, need not fear the one, nor the other: For Sickneſs and Death are in her power, to inflict or reſtrain them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> A Perſon delivered from his Impriſonment in <hi>France.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Holy Angel delivered <hi>Peter</hi> out of Priſon, but the Queen of Angels,<note place="margin">1428.</note> delivered the Perſon whereof I am about to write: <hi>William Moſtier</hi> travell'd from <hi>Picardy,</hi> his own Country, towards the Province of <hi>Poictiers</hi> (there was then a ſharp War between <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) he unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell into the latter, and was led Captive to the City of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> where he was impriſoned in a deep Dungeon, and had two Irons put upon his Legs! He remained there ten Months, becauſe he could not raiſe a ranſom of Eighty Golden Crowns. Being in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the Bleſſed Virgin of <hi>Halle</hi> came into his mind, whoſe name and worſhip was then famous in <hi>Picardy,</hi> he prayed heartily that by her aſſiſtance he might be delivered from this filth and darkneſs. Hereupon he fell into a ſweet ſleep, and waking in the Morning (oh wonderful thing!) he found himſelf not only out of the Priſon, and free from his bonds, but three Miles diſtant from St. <hi>Michael.</hi> Whileſt he being aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, ſtood contemplating of his deliverance, there was ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Troopers came thither, and amongſt them Captain <hi>Turnbul,</hi> who immediately knowing him, ſaid unto him, Are not you our Priſoner? how came you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58679:15"/>what power, or Subtilty, did you get out of Priſon. To which he anſwered, Sir I'le tell you the Truth; <q>I was not delivered by humane power or craft, but my deliverance was performed by a higher hand, by the B. Virgin, whom I invoked; ſhe brought me hither unknown to my ſelf, when I was aſleep; I beſeech you that you would, and I truſt that you will further ſo good a Work.</q> The Captain and his Companions, being moved by this Relation, and aſſured of the truth thereof, gave him a Paſsport, wherein they teſtified this Miracle; which Paſs <hi>Willier Moſtier</hi> brought to <hi>Halle,</hi> and with Thankſgiving offered it up to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, well-knowing that he was delivered out of the Priſon, and from the Iron Bands, but was bound in other obligations to the Bleſſed Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> A Woman wonderfully preſerved from Death, under a Wheel of a Mill.</head>
               <p>AND had not <hi>Catharine,</hi> the Wife of <hi>John Maſſart,</hi> great reaſon to thank the B. Virgin? <hi>John Maſſart</hi> was both a Carpenter and Miller, and lived near the Abby of <hi>Lobes,</hi> in <hi>Henegow.</hi> He went to work abroad, and left the charge of the Mill to his Wife; ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Mill to go ſlowly for want of Water, drew up the Sluce, and let in a rapid Stream, to turn the Wheel more ſwiftly. The Plank whereon ſhe ſtood broke from under her, and ſhe was preſently driven under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Wheel, by the force of the Water; where ſhe re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed. We muſt not omit to remark that ſhe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Child, and her time almoſt conſummated. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> up her heart to the B. Virgin of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58679:16"/>
                  <hi>Halle,</hi> and found that a ſecret friend is a ſtrong bridge; for the Mother of God preſerved her half an hour, not only from drowning by the Water, but alſo from the cruſhing of the Wheel. By this time her Husband came, who by his complaints ſummoned to his aid, and for Witneſſes, the Neighbours, the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the place, and ſome Religious of the Abby of <hi>Lobes.</hi> They drew her out of the Water, not expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to find her alive, but ſhe came out alive and very well, thanking a thouſand times the B. Virgin, who had ſo preſerved her, that a few days after ſhe was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of a Beautiful Child, to the aſtoniſhment of all that heard of it; that under ſo heavy a weight the Child was neither bruiſed nor wounded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> A Taylor having ſwallowed his Needle, was delivered from the danger attending it by the Bleſſed Virgin.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BArtholomew Broeck,</hi> a Taylor of the City of <hi>Denre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monde,</hi> being buſied about his work, put his Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and Thred into his Mouth, that he might have his hands free; being intent on his work, and forgetting his Needle, he unhappily ſwallowed both that and the Thred. Afterwards he complained to his Wife, who conſulted the Phyſicians and followed their advice, but in vain: After it had remained in his Body four days, he went to <hi>Mechlen</hi> to his Brother, who was a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian; but he could not force it out of his Body by any Drinks or Purge. It happened that on a <hi>Saturday</hi> his Brother made a ſmall Feaſt, to entertain his ſorrowful Gueſts, which being done, the Bell Rung to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which is called <hi>the Praiſe of the B. Virgin;</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58679:16"/>went unto the Church, but <hi>Bartholomew</hi> ſtayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind: As he was muſing, our Lady of <hi>Halle</hi> came into his thoughts, he preſently ſent a ſervent Vow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, and immediately he ſelt ſomething between his Teeth, and pulled out the Needle and Thred. He joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhewed his Brother this great Miracle, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully viſited the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle;</hi> and he had great reaſon ſo to do, for his life had hung many days upon a Needle and Thred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> A Nobleman preſerved from Death, upon the Sea.</head>
               <p>THE Ship that carried <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Fortunes, was not ſo proſperous as that wherein a Burgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Nobleman of <hi>Monick,</hi> in <hi>Bavaria,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from the <hi>Hely Land.</hi> Being upon the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, he ſell ſick of a dangerous diſeaſe, which in the judgment of the Seamen was incurable: They had reſolved to throw him overboard for food for the Fiſhes. Another Nobleman perceived their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and was very ſorry for it; he went to the ſick Perſon, and ſound him not only ſpeechleſs but almoſt ſenſleſs; he comforted him as much as he could, and told him that in the City of <hi>Halle</hi> the B. Virgin was worſhipped, that ſhe had done many good Offices for men, and was a publick reſuge, and common defence to the afflicted, adviſing him to truſt in her; and if he could not with his mouth, he ſhould at leaſt in his heart make a vow unto her; and told him that he ſhould immediately regain his health. The Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man underſtanding him, ſighed from the bottom of his heart, and prayed unto her, and at the ſame time he ſaw a company of evil Spirits hovering over the Ship;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58679:17"/>alſo he ſaw beſides a Woman of an honourable Miene, and a beautiful Countenance, ſtanding before him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in one Arm a little Child, and in the other hand a burning Candle; which ſhe had hardly ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spirits betook themſelves to flight. He felt the influence of her preſence, for his ſpeech returned, his diſtemper abated, and his ſtrength was augmented to his great comfort, and the aſtoniſhment of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; in ſhort, he was reſtored to his Health, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his own Country. Then it was his firſt and principal care to perform his obligations to the B. Virgin; to that end he and his Servant went to <hi>Netherland,</hi> with Teſtimonies of an extraordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, for he came and returned barefoot that long way, which is almoſt as broad as all <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> A Carman falling into the Water with his Cart was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from Death.</head>
               <p>ALthough Salt is an Emblem of Wiſdom,<note place="margin">144<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> yet here comes a Carman with a whole Cart-load there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; who was not wiſe enough to foreſee his misfortune, much leſs to prevent it: But I believe this danger befel him, that the Name and Praiſe of the B. Virgin might be the more ſpread in <hi>Long-Champ</hi> in <hi>Walſch Brabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Carman being driving his Cart over a Bridge in <hi>Long-Champ,</hi> it fell in, he ſeeing the fall approach, endeavour'd to ſupport the Cart, but the weight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of forced him along with it, and Horſe, and Cart, and he under it, fell into the River: God ordered it ſo that there was a Girl near to the place, who ſeeing the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, called for help; but it was a long time e're ſhe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58679:17"/>could get People enough together. The Magiſtrate himſelf, and ſeveral beſide, run to the place, and got out the Horſe and Cart, and found unexpectedly the Carman, who had laid under it; they all thought that he was as well ſtifled by the weight of the Cart, as drowned by the Water. They carried him to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Houſe, where they ſtript him, but he was ſo far gone that he did not feel them; no ſymptoms of life appear'd in him. One or two of the Spectators, out of a Chriſtian Compaſſion, recommended this poor man to our Lady, making ſome Vows at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>This Devotion, although it came from perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eoncerned, was acceptable to the <hi>Holy Mother of God,</hi> and found a return of Mercy; for the Carman came to himſelf, and a little while after unloaded his Cart. He alſo went to <hi>Halle</hi> to thank our Lady for this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. This Carmans mean Cart, by this Miracle was rendred more Illuſtrious than the Triumphant Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> A Perſon preſerved from ſeveral dangers, in and after Battel.</head>
               <p>WHat will you ſee in the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> but Hymns of Armies (ſaid the Bridegroom) that is Thankſgivings to the B. Virgin for Victories, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from Dangers, in the midſt of Enemies. A Wonderful Hiſtory which was acted in <hi>Picardy,</hi> will confirm this. The Earl of St. <hi>Paul</hi> (famous of that time for his Valour and Noble Deſcent) was to go from <hi>Chaſtelet</hi> to <hi>Campaign,</hi> to the <hi>Daulphin</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> There being then War between the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh;</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58679:18"/>on a <hi>Saturday</hi> in the morning, he ſent his Cook, Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and Quarter-Maſter, to provide Lodging, and to prepare for his Reception. Theſe three diſcovered a Party of the Enemy, ſixty or ſeventy in number, that were ſtealing the Cattel: They returned ſpeedily, and advertis'd the Earl of the danger; he being a ſtout man, cauſed his men immediately to Arm themſelves, and mount their Horſes; he being the moſt forward, rid out before, with <hi>John de Gertru,</hi> a truſty Servant, in ſuch haſte, that <hi>John</hi> was not well Armed; the reſt followed them by one or two at a time; their whole number being about Eighty. They purſued the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but they found them together with thoſe which came out of their Ambuſcade, to be 1500 ſtrong. <hi>John</hi> firſt perceived their number, and deſired his Maſter (who burned to fight them) to return, whilſt he would detain them with Skirmiſhing: The Earl would not conſent to that, but fell upon them, and they upon him; <hi>John</hi> was ſhot in his Arm by two Croſs-Bow Arrows; and looking about him, once more to admoniſh his Lord, a third Arrow hit him on the Head, upon which he fell from his Horſe. The Earl ſeeing that the Enemy was too unequal, and knowing that delay would but inflame the Enemy, put ſpur to his Horſe, and endeavour'd to reach the next Town.</p>
               <p>The Earl here was troubled at nothing ſo much as the loſs of ſuch a truſty Servant, thinking that he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly dy'd of thoſe three wounds; but the goodneſs of God, and the mercy of the B. Virgin preſerved him, contrary to all expectation, yea even beyond belief; for whilſt he lay among the men and horſes, he had continually in his mouth the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe who aſſiſted ſo many, would not forſake
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58679:18"/>him in this apparent danger; he crept upon his hands and ſeet unto the next way, where he lay very feeble Here again aroſe a new difficulty, for three of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies party came to plunder the Dead, and finding this miſerable Man, they took his Money, Rings and Cloathes, and cleaved his Head with a Sword. Being thus wounded, he ſtill retained his life and hope, again beſeeching the B. Virgin, as alſo St. <hi>Barbara,</hi> that they would be ſo gracious as to afford him an opportunity of Confeſſion: This Prayer ſo moved the Souldiers themſelves, that they ſerved him in this requeſt, for they ſeeing by chance a Prieſt, called him to the wounded perſon, that he ſhould prepare him for death, for they intended to kill him. As it alſo happened af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, one of them endeavouring to cut his Throat, but the B. Virgin ſo averted the Blade, that only the Coller of his Shirt was cut. The Prieſt did his beſt endeavour to beg his life of them, whereupon the Souldiers retired, and the Prieſt got him to an adjacent Barn, dreſſing his wounds, as much as the time would permit. There came alſo another Party of the Enemy, but there was amongſt them ſome Honourable Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Commanders, but they did not meddle with them. At the approach of theſe the Prieſt had run away. After they were gone the three Villains came again, and ſeeing him alive, ſtruck him a very hard blow, by which they thought they had killed him, as indeed they had, without the aſſiſtance of the Mother of God. Going on their way, they drew the body in a great rage to the River: The B. Virgin comforted him, and adviſed him to ſeign himſelf dead; here they threw him into the Water, and becauſe they would be ſure to kill him they pricked him with a Lance. The B. Virgin alſo averted this puſh, and carried her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58679:19"/>unto a ſmall dirty Iſland, that jets its Head a little above Water, where he lay three hours; the coldneſs of the water, and his loſs of blood by nine mortal Wounds rendred him quite ſtiff. The Prieſt which had heard his Confeſſion, like a good <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> out of compaſſion, went to ſeek him, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the track of his blood, came to the water, where, to his great grief, he could not find him. I deſire that the Courteous Reader would not be offended with the length of this Relation, but that he would pleaſe to ſearch after, and exalt the powerful arm of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> with Patience and Aſtoniſhment. The Prieſt ſtanding here comfortleſs, caſt his eyes towards the little Iſland, where he ſaw ſomething, but he could not diſcern whether it was a man or ſome evil Spirits; arming himſelf with the ſign of the Holy Croſs he called aloud, <hi>I conjure you in Gods Name, if you are a Chriſtian, to ſpeak or make ſome ſign:</hi> Hereupon <hi>John</hi> lifted up his arm and ſatisfied the Prieſt, who went up to the Neck in water, and brought him to a dry place, and immediately run to the next Town to procure a Wagon, and ſome men, to carry him thither, where he was cured, and came in perſon to the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle,</hi> with his mouth full of Thankſgiving, and yet the thanks was beneath the benefit which he received; for he was four times preſerved from death, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently gained four lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58679:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> A Gentleman was delivered out of Priſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilip</hi> of <hi>Cleve,</hi> a young Gentleman, naturallly, though illegally deſcended from that Illuſtrious Houſe, lived at <hi>Dijon</hi> in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and was very much addicted to War and Arms, but he was not ſo fortunate as valiant, for he was taken by the French, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned at <hi>Vaucouleur</hi> in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in a Tower 80 Cubits high; his Ranſom, being a Gentleman, was 500 Crowns, which being too great a ſumm for his Eſtate, cauſed in him not only a grief of mind, but a bodily diſeaſe alſo. Once when his dinner was brought unto him, he fell into a ſweet ſleep which continued until the next day at Noon, and then he was awaked by the Keeper of the Priſon, who admoniſhed him to eat the portion of Meat which was allotted him; but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which he had received from a Viſion in his ſleep, averted his appetite from it. His Viſion was as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: He thought that he ſaw himſelf lying upon the ſteps of our Ladys Chappel, pouring his fervent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers out before her Image; which were heard; for the B. Virgin gave him hope of an approaching deliverance. Being alone, he fell upon his knees, beſeeching the B. Virgin that this dream might proceed to a happy event. Hereupon he took a bone from the Beef which was allotted him, and uſed it inſtead of a File, and touched therewith the Irons that were about his Neck, Hands and Feet, and broke them. He tyed his Linnen and Cloathes together, with which he let himſelf down from the Tower, but it was not long enough; he ventur'd a ſteep fall without any damage. Now to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58679:20"/>finiſh happily that deliverance which was begun, he hid himſelf in the next Wood, and made uſe of the darkneſs of the Night to fly in; his flight continued three days, and at their end he came hungry, disfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and naked as he was, to thank the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> A Servant was delivered from the Gallows.</head>
               <p>ALthough (according to the Heathens) <hi>Bellona</hi> is the Goddeſs of War, yet ſhe muſt lay her Arms and Laws at the foot of <hi>Mary;</hi> and thoſe which ſhe hath ordained to death,<note place="margin">1604.</note> the B. Virgin can preſerve alive. As it happened in <hi>Weerdt,</hi> where the Mutiners were 5000 ſtrong, and had retired to a place very well fortified. Theſe men, although they had trodden under feet all Princely Laws, and Obligations of Obedience, yet they could not effect their deſign, without eſtabliſhing new, and more ſevere Laws. They forbid the hindering, or injuring of thoſe which brought and ſold Proviſion upon pain of death. A Young man of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>John,</hi> went to the Market to buy Herrings; as ſoon as he had received the Herrings he intended to have paid for them, but he was driven from his place by the croud, before he could give the ſeller his Money: A Trumpeter ſaw this, but knew not that it was innocently done; and being allured by the 25 Crowns which was promiſed to the diſcoverer of any breaker of this Law, he denvered, and accuſed him to the Officers; who in a Councel of War unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly condemned him. Guilty or not guilty, he muſt now be hanged. Seeing that there was no Juſtice
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58679:20"/>on Earth, he ſent his Prayers to Heaven for Mercy, and ſaid, <hi>O Mighty Queen of Heaven, which art worſhipped at Halle, as thou haſt ſeveral times defended the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, ſo defend my Innocence;</hi> and immediately he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſtrong confidence in her Mercy. He was led by the Executioner to the Gallows, tyed up, and turned off the Ladder. He was alſo hanged with a double Rope; one Cord broke, and the other was likely to break. Although the Spectators eſteemed this to be a Miracle, yet the Executioner leaped upon his ſhoulders to ſtrangle him; a Souldier ſeeing this, ran up the Ladder, and cut the Rope with his Sword. Thus <hi>John</hi> was delivered, and came and bowed his condemned Head before the B. Virgin of <hi>Halle,</hi> and thanked her for the deliverance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> A Nun cured of a Convulſion of the Sinews.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ADriana Serraets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1602</note> a Noble and Religious Nun of <hi>Vorſt,</hi> being about 22 years of age, and in very good health, was ſuddenly taken with a Convulſion of the Sinews; this tormented her ſo grievouſly, that ſhe could not reſt by day nor night, neither the Ingenuity of the Phyſician, nor the Experience of the Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could afford her any redreſs; an evident ſign that all humane help muſt give place, that we may aſcribe the Glory to the B. Virgin only. To that end (with the Approbation of her Abbeſs) ſhe ſent a Pious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in her ſtead to <hi>Halle,</hi> who in her Name, and for the regaining of her Health, ſhould offer up a gift, and cauſe the Sacrifice of the Maſs to be recited. Oh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, but true event! At the ſame time that the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58679:21"/>offered the gift, at the very inſtant, when the Prieſt was ſerving for her at the Altar at <hi>Halle,</hi> her health was reſtored her upon the Quire at <hi>Vorſt;</hi> ſhe was then employed according to her cuſtom, in praiſing of God; having regained her Health, ſhe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a joyful <hi>Te-Deum</hi> to be ſung.</p>
               <p>The Dutch Author relates ſome Miracles which are teſtified by the Inſcriptions, and Paintings of the Chappel, but they being not ſo fully related as the precedent Relations; I ſhall only conclude with one of the Inſcriptions, which is as as followeth.</p>
               <q>D. O. M. <hi>&amp;</hi> M. M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. HEnricus ab Etten Antwerpiae, menſe Octobri Anno <hi>1575.</hi> Peſtilenti febri laborans, deſtitutus a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis, cum peregrinationem ad aedem Deiparae Hallis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram voviſſer, praeſenti coeleſtis opis miraculo, inox cadem levatus, hanc tabellam tanti beneficii grati memorem, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae miſericordiae palam teſtem humile devotione collocat, conſecratque.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
